General Manuscripts Miscellaneous Collection, 1502-2012: Finding Aid C0140
Manuscripts Division
- Correspondence from Dorothy and Simon Bussy to Auguste Bréal, 1919-1940; Bussy, Dorothy, 1865-1960; Bussy, Simon, 1870-1954; 1 folder (Box B-001748, Folder 11)
  In Simon Bussy's letters, he primarily writes to Bréal of the people in his social circles, of their personalities and goings-on, with a lesser focus on his painting, art, and literary interests. He writes about André Gide, Somerset Maugham, and Henri Matisse, as well as of Roger Fry's death, and Roger Martin du Gard's post-Nobel attempts at anonymity.
  Bussy
  Dorothy Bussy (née Strachey) (1865-1960) was an English novelist and translator, close to the Bloomsbury Group. She was educated at the Marie Souvestre girls' school at Les Ruches, Fontainebleau, France and later in England when Souvestre removed the school to Allenswood there. She was later a teacher with Souvestre.
  In 1903, Dorothy married the French painter, Simon Bussy (1870–1954), who knew Matisse, and was on the fringes of the Bloomsbury circle.
  Bussy anonymously published one novel, Olivia, in 1949, printed by the Hogarth Press, the publishing house founded by Leonard and Virginia Woolf. Bussy's novel was translated into French and appeared in France with an introduction by Rosamond Lehmann.
  Albert Simon Aimé Bussy (1870-1954) was a French painter who married the English novelist Dorothy Bussy. He knew and painted many members of the Bloomsbury circle.
  Bussy was born in Dole, France, and went from the drawing school there to Gustave Moreau's studio in the École des beaux-arts de Paris, where he met and became friends with Henri Matisse. He showed a Portrait of Albert Machado in 1896. In 1897 he had his first solo exhibition at the Durand-Ruel gallery in Paris.
  In 1901 Bussy visited London, where he came into contact with members of some English artistic circles, especially the Bloomsbury Group, and where he met Dorothy Strachey, who became his wife in 1903. Shortly after the wedding Simon and Dorothy moved to Roquebrune Cap Martin, in the south of France, where their house soon became a meeting point for French and English artists, writers and intellectuals.
  Bussy was successful in the 1920s and 1930s, but his appreciation by both the public and critics declined after this time. He died in London in 1954, at the age of 88.
  Artists -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Artists -- France -- Correspondence; Painters -- France -- Correspondence; Art historians -- France -- Biography; Journalists -- France -- Biography; Bloomsbury group.; Authors, English -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Bréal, Auguste, 1869-1941
- Johannes Storm Account Book, East Fishkill, Dutchess County, New York, 1770-1839; 1800-1839; Storm, Johannes (1765-1835); Storm, Charles G.; 1 folder (Box B-001748, Folder 12)
  Purchased from Dan Casavant Rare Books in 2021 (AM 2021-58).
  This handwritten 230-page ledger includes personal and business accounts of the expenses of Johannes Storm, a brickmaker from East Fishkill/Stormville in Dutchess County, New York. Following the death of Johannes Storm in 1835, the ledger was continued by his son, Charles G. Storm, through 1839.
  The ledger contains a significant number of entries for various construction projects in the area, including Johannes Storm's house and the Hopewell Consistory & Pine Grove Woolen Factory, as well as production for Dutchess County war regiments, and accounts for local residents, soldiers, including many former Revolutionary War veterans and War of 1812 servicemen, tradesmen, and workers.
  Many of the workers documented likely include indentured servants as well as free and enslaved African Americans. Some were seasonal and tenant farmers or sharecroppers who were often hired for terms of 7 months. Most worked in the fields and on the farm; some worked in the household.
  Members of the Schouten, Johnson, Freeman, and Collins families, who were likely African American based on information from a cemetery the Storm family used for individuals they had enslaved as well as census records, include: Abraham Schouten, Simon Schouton, Anne Schouten Jerry or Jirry Schouten; Joe or Joseph Johnson (page 44), Isabel Johnson, Jane Johnson (page 164), and Betsy Johnson (who died in 1848 at the age of 65); York Freeman, Joe Freeman, Samuel or Sam Freeman, France Freeman, and Robert Freeman; and Edward Collins and Truby Collins. Single names of individuals who were likely enslaved workers or indentured servants as their days of work are also accounted for against their provisions/accounts, include: Betsy (Spencer?), Betty (Johnson?), Hannah (Tomkins?), Harry (Gilbert?), Henry Cook, Henry Merit, Hiram Howard, Edward Howard, William Dugo, William Slocum, Old Slocum, Polly Jacox, Rufus Ebens, Sally Brown, Timothy Wood, Caty, Diane, Dick, Dinah, Francis, Jo, Massy, Phillis, Pompey, Pomp, Raymond, Stephen, Terrah or Jirrah, Terry, Henry, Lenah ("purchased 1808 to serve 10 years; sold to Mr. George Green," page 255), Betsy Morse (began to work in 1833), Henry How ("came here at 11 years old; 1823 – work for victuals and clothing till age 16"), Jim ("purchased 1809 – to serve 14 years"), Joe ("purchased 1812 – to serve 12 years"), Frank, Phebe Haff ("cash paid Dr. Gilbert; credit by house work"), and Mehala.
  Regular tenant farmers include: John Van Alst, Sam Henderson, and Francis Dence. Other accounts include those for Lewis Germany Bass Viol ("paid to Mr. Mosely teach singing school"), and Wallace Patrick.
  Other local individuals documented include: Jonathan Lee, Isaac Adriance, Thomas Doughty, Abraham Schouton, John Carman, Asahel Thrasher, and Theodorus Adriance, among others.
  This description comes from information provided by the dealer.
  This item was part of the Fred W. Haida Collection (of Putnam County, New York) as noted in a stamp on endpaper. It had also been part of the collection of Dave Englund of Seattle.
  Coert Horton Farm Account Book and Diary
  This item contains some descriptions of the purchase and sale of enslaved African Americans.
  Storm
  Johannes Storm (1765-1835) was a Revolutionary War veteran and brickmaker. The son of Garret Storm, Johannes was from a wealthy family of Dutch ancestry from East Fishkill/Stormville, Dutchess County, New York. Johannes married Susanna Brinckerhoff (1772-1827) in April 1793. They had a least one child, Charles G. Storm.
  Son of Johannes Storm (1765-1835) of East Fishkill /Stormville, Dutchess County, New York. Charles ran the family estate after his father's death.
  Ledgers (account books) -- 19th century; African Americans -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Dutchess County (N.Y.) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Construction industry -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Free African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Slaves -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Indentured servants -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Sharecropping -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; African Americans -- Employment -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources
- Coert Horton Farm Account Book and Diary, East Fishkill, Dutchess County, New York, 1801-1843; Horton, Coert (1768-1843); 1 folder (Box L-000030, Folder 1)
  This handwritten account book, numbering about 236 pages, includes a substantial and detailed record of Major Coert Horton's 725-acre farm in East Fishkill, Dutchess County, New York, and among other workers, documents free African American laborers Horton hired.
  The first section of the ledger, about 34 pages with some overlap, begins in 1801 by John Heaton (1776-1827) of Throgs Neck, New York and contains the name, on the first inside page, of his son Samuel Cooper Heaton (born 1811), who apparently took over the ledger and the management of the family estate. Other names listed include Isaac and Jonah Heaton.
  The latter sections, beginning with a two page alphabetical index, is a record of the Coert Horton Farm at Hopewell Junction in East Fishkill, which included an orchard, sheep, horses, grain, a smoke house, strawberries, and other goods, where Coert hired a number of individuals to work on the farm. Some are clearly identified as African Americans. The most frequently hired individual is identified as Philip Freeman (Philip is sometimes spelled with two "l"s, and Freeman is also spelled "Freman") who also lived at the farm. An entry (page 30) beginning with the date October 23, 1841, and carrying through to March 12, 1842 lists the days Philip worked and his wages.
  Other individuals spcifically identified as "black" include: Henry, Jane Ann, and Martin (son John). Those described as "coloured men" include: John H. Colden (there is a single page receipt loosely inserted for a payment on June 3, 1842 for "1 pair fine boots 22/ - box blacking/ 02.88"), Peter Dickerson, Martin Colin, John Colin, (son of Martin), and Peter Warren. Tenant farmers or sharecroppers include the Sedore Family- Casmer, Carmi and Charles; Peter Rickey; Levi Miller; and Eli Reed, among others. Towards the end of the ledger, there is a full page given to the written contract between Peter Rickey and Coert Horton, in which Rickey agrees to work for Horton for a one year term, for the sum of $120, commencing April 1, 1842; it is signed by both parties. Names of other employees include Pegga Maria; Mahala Breeder; Alson Purdy; Maddison Smith; Rachel Lee; Jesse Tibbit; John Titus; Brown Miller; and William Burtis.
  In the many entries recorded between 1840 and 1843, names that appear repeatedly include Barbary Van Wyck, Martha Dorlan, Levi Miller, Eli Reed, and Charles Hazelton. There are also accounts related to several Horton family members.
  The page before the alphabetical index includes a large account for Richard Rapelje who was connected to Betty Johnson, an enslaved worked of the Storm family of East Fishkill in Dutchess County. The Hortons and Rapelje families are related.
  The last 50 pages of the ledger includes various business-related tables and memoranda and cash paid out accounts.
  From the "Fred W. Haida Collection" of Putnam County, New York, stamped on end paper. The item was later owned by Antipodean Books, Garrison, New York.
  Johannes Storm Account Book, East Fishkill, Dutchess County, New York, 1770-1839
  Horton
  Coert Horton, son of Jacob Horton, was born March 15, 1768 in Dutchess County, New York. He died December 23, 1843 (aged 75) and is buried at the Van Wyck Cemetery in Hopewell Junction, Dutchess County, New York. Known as Major Coert Horton, he served in Dutchess County under Lieutenant Col. Commandant John B. Van Wyck's regiment as a Captain in 1800. He married Ann Maria Rappleje at Hopewell March 27, 1833 with whom he had 5 children: Elizabeth Horton (1793–1794), Jacob Horton (1797–1865), Richard Van Wyck Horton (1799–1822), John Brinkerhoff Horton 1803–1829, and Jane Horton (1806–1826).
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Dutchess County (N.Y.) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Ledgers (account books) -- 19th century; Free African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; African Americans -- Employment -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Sharecropping -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Heaton, John (1776-1827); Heaton, Samuel Cooper (1811-); Freeman, Philip
- Photograph Album of U. U. T. W. (United Union of Telephone Workers) Women Telephone Workers on Strike Near Lincoln (Ashland), Nebraska, 1946-1949; 1 folder (Box B-001796, Folder 1)
  Purchased from Michael Vinson Americana in 2021 (AM 2022-085).
  This photograph album contains 116 black and white photographic prints, each captioned with identifying names on black album pages in white ink. Some individual's positions with the company are also included. The album belonged to a woman who worked at the Ashland office of the Lincoln Telephone and Telegraph Company, and begins with both individual and group portrait photographs of her coworkers. Most are in front of the steps of the telephone office, and the album begins with the caption, "The Telephone Gang, Ashland."
  The majority of the photographs are of the Lincoln Telephone and Telegraph Company strikers who participated in the 1947 Telephone strike that took place from April 7 to May 19, 1947. Most of the photographs are of employees on the picket line with signs. Besides the 1947 Telephone strike, there are other organizing photographs of labor union members attending mass meetings of the United Union of Telephone Workers (U. U. T. W.), at the union office headquarters, and at city hall and the capitol. At the end of the album are photographs of the company events, including Christmas parties from 1947 and 1948, and the wedding of Virgil Bowman and Dorothy Nelson in 1949.
  The people identified in the album include the creator, although her photograph is captioned simply with "myself". Other people identified in the album include: Jean Gilmore, John Potter (manager), Audrey Neal, Evelyn Sprague (chief operator), Genevieve Wood, Helen Boldt, Lillian Campbell, Lola Hetherington, Ruth Marcks (strike captain), Mabel Volpp (strike captain), Delores Glover (strike captain), Elaine Scovell (supervisor), Lawanna Graham, Margaret Micloski, Onita Clausen, Ruth Hetherington, Vera Wasson, and many others.
  Labor unions -- United States -- 20th century; Women labor union members; Photograph albums -- United States -- 20th century.; Photographic prints; United Union of Telephone Workers
- Rosa Lee Miller Photograph Album, 1936-1940; Miller, Rosa Lee; 1 folder (Box L-000030, Folder 2)
  Purchased from William Reese Company in 2021 (AM 2022-086).
  This photograph album, belonging to a young Black woman named Rosa Lee Miller, contains black and white photographic prints and ephemera documenting some of Miller's life in Princeton, New Jersey. The album documents her years at Princeton High School (Class of 1939), including an image of her in her commencement outfit, and features numerous photos of her with family and friends. Some of the photographs are captioned with identifying names, and include Pearl Bass, Quida Raney, Dot Joiner, and Farell Johnson. There are numerous scenes at the beach and other leisure activities. Some of the photographs, including one captioned "Hunter Building," are from St. Augustine's College, a historically Black college in Raleigh, North Carolina.
  The ephemera includes programs from Miller's high school graduation ceremony, as well as a program for the senior play. There are invitations to dances at Black clubs in Princeton, along with a few dance cards and a newspaper clipping about one of the dances. Besides these Princeton items, the album also contains ephemera from historically black colleges and universities (HBCUs). Among this ephemera from HBCUs are tickets and programs for tennis championships in 1938 and 1939, at Lincoln University and Hampton Institute, respectively. Other items include a basketball schedule for Shaw University, a newspaper clipping about New Jersey men on the Howard University basketball team, and a ticket from a Howard- Lincoln football game. Also among the ephemera are correspondence, a small self-help pamphlet entitled "Your Life in the Making," by Joy Elmer Morgan, and invitations.
  African American women -- New Jersey -- photographs; African American girls -- Education; African American universities and colleges -- New Jersey -- 20th century; Photograph albums -- United States -- 20th century.; Ephemera -- 20th century; Scrapbooks -- New Jersey -- 20th century; Princeton High School (Princeton, N.J.)
- Roehl Family Photograph Album, circa 1920-1935; Roehl family; 1 folder (Box B-001796, Folder 2)
  Consists of a family photograph album containing 160 silver gelatin photographs documenting the lives of Yup'ik and Athabaskan (Kenai Dena'ina) communities in and around Iliamna, Togiak, Quinhagak, Akutan, Wrangell Narrows, and along the Kuskokwim River in Alaska in the early 20th century. The album documents the large extended family of Frederick Johann Roehl (1859-1924), a German American settler, and Mary A. Wassalie (1882-1923), a Yup'ik woman from the Athabaskan village of Iliamna in Alaska. They operated a grocery store in Iliamna Portage (later called Williamsport) at the head of Iliamna Bay on Cook Inlet. The album may have been assembled by Charles Frederick Roehl (1903-1979) and Marie Ann Roehl Millett (born 1902), two of the Roehls' children.
  The album includes photographs taken at the Quinhagak School, including a "baby class" of small children with husky puppies, and at the Kanakanak Orphanage, where Aleut, Yup'ik, Athabaskan, and settler children whose parents died during the 1918 influenza pandemic were gathered. A few images show Dr. Linus Hiram French, including one with Dorothy and Robert Glass in the tuberculosis quarantine quarters at Kanakanak Hospital. Other images show Togiak village girls, possibly at the Inuit villages Togiagamute (Togiagamiut) and Togiak Station on Togiak Bay, as well as another village on Ingelichoak River. Children mentioned by name include Wassili Nounachthluh, Andrew Aghuhbuktah, Anecia Aguvuluk, Lulu, Sasa, Mamie, Mumuli, Robert, Peter, Mike, and Sam. Other family members, friends, and neighbors whose names are listed in captions throughout the album include Evan Powghiak and his father, Nicholas Henry, a medicine man; Julia Agnes Millett (1928-2015), daughter of Marie Ann Roehl and Hugh H. Millett; Frederick Roehl III; Old Big Chief and Old Sophie (Togiak); the Kinney family; and a funeral procession for William Richteroff. One photograph also likely shows the older children of Frederick Johann Roehl, including Mary, Charles, Sofia, Fred, and Henry.
  Other images show Alaska Native women cutting and drying salmon and weaving baskets, whaling operations, reindeer herds, huskies, walrus heads, the M.S. Discoverer, the Harding Glacier, a family potato garden, and a bush plane. While most of the images were taken in Alaska, there are also photographs of Washington state, including a hand-coloured image of a ship at a dock in Vaugh, Washington, and family members at Ruby Beach on the Olympic Peninsula.
  Purchased from Zephyr Used & Rare Books in 2021 (AM 2022-083).
  The Roehl family was a family of Alaska Native and European descent based in the Athabaskan village of Iliamna, Alaska, in the late 19th and early 20th century. Frederick Johann Roehl (1859-1924), a German American settler, and Mary A. Wassalie (1882-1923, also known as Mary Apachulook), a Yup'ik woman from Iliamna, operated a grocery store and transported freight from Iliamna Bay to Pile Bay using dog sleds. They had eight children, including Charles Frederick Roehl (1903-1979) and Marie Ann Roehl (born 1902). Marie Ann Roehl married Hugh Harrell Millett (1892-1979), a white fisherman who moved to Alaska from Washington state. Charles Frederick Roehl married Parascovia Valun Rickteroff (1901-1996), a Kenai Dena'ina woman who was the daughter of William Rickteroff (born 1851) and Mariia Semenova Bytskunyshin (1855–1914).
  Alaska Natives -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Aleuts -- Alaska -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Athapascan Indians -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Quinhagak (Alaska) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Togiak (Alaska) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Village of Iliamna -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Washington (State) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Photograph albums -- 20th century; Kanakanak Hospital
- Clark Kinsey Photographs of Logging in the Pacific Northwest, circa 1930s; Kinsey, Clark, 1877-1956; 1 folder (Box P-000151, Folder 9)
  Consists of a group of nine large-format photographs depicting lumbering operations of the St. Paul & Tacoma Lumber Company, the Pacific National Lumber Company, and the Simpson Lumber Company in the Pacific Northwest. Most of the images are posed shots of timber workers standing with logs and equipment. All of the photographs are captioned in the negative, and two have annotations on the back identifying some of the workers. Images are captioned as follows: "No. 2. Camp #8. St. Paul & Tacoma Lmbr Co. / C. Kinsey Photo Seattle;" "No. 5. St. Paul & Tacoma Lmbr Co. / C. Kinsey Photo;" "St. Paul and Tacoma Lbr. Co #5 / Kinsey Photo;" "No. 7 St. Paul & Tacoma Lmbr Co / C. Kinsey Photo;" "Pacific National Lbr Co. / C. Kinsey Photo / No. 660;" "Pacific National Lbr. Co. / C. Kinsey Photo / No. 665;" "Kinsey Photo / No. 5 Simpson Lbr. Co. Camp 3;" "Simpson Camp #3 / Kinsey Photo #12;" and "Simpson Camp #3 / Kinsey #12."
  Purchased from Tavistock Books in 2021 (AM 2022-082).
  Loggers -- Northwest, Pacific -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Logging -- Washington (State) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Logging -- Washington (State) -- photographs; photographs -- 20th century; St. Paul & Tacoma Lumber Company; Pacific National Lumber Company; Simpson Lumber Company
- Manuscript Documenting Women's Contributions toward an American Bible Society Membership for Reverend Chester Colton, 1819 February 16; 1 folder (Box B-001796, Folder 3)
  Consists of a manuscript subscription list recording the contributions of over thirty women in Brentwood, Connecticut, towards the purchase of a lifetime membership in the American Bible Society for Reverend Chester Colton, a Congregationalist pastor. Women who contributed to the fund include Catharine, Sarah, Dorothy, Elizabeth, Mary, and Betsey Dudley; Betsey Kimball; Elizabeth and Judith Morrill; Mehitable, Sarah, and Anna Thing; Sarah Colcord; Hannah and Betsey Marshall; Sophia, Betsey, and Rachel Robinson; Eunice Leavitt; Hannah Ranney; Rebecah and Sarah Graves; Rebeccah and Lydia Sandborn; Rachel and Lydia Tuck; Nabby Fellows; Abigail Veazey; Martha Gilman; Sarah Hook; and Lydia Smith.
  Purchased from Garrett Scott, Bookseller, in 2021 (AM 2022-090).
  Congregationalists -- Connecticut -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Women -- Connecticut -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Connecticut -- Church history -- 19th century -- Sources; Subscription lists -- 19th century; American Bible society; Colton, Chester, Reverend
- Photographs and Notebook Documenting Camp Stewart during the United States Army Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1917; 1 folder (Box B-001796, Folder 4)
  Consists of a group of sixty-seven photographs and a small notebook compiled by an unidentified 1st Pennsylvania Cavalry soldier documenting military life at Camp Stewart in 1917. Camp Stewart was an army camp in West Texas established by the United States Army for the defense of El Paso and the western Texas-Mexico border during General John J. Pershing's expedition (1916-1917) against Pancho Villa during the Mexican Revolution (1910-1920). This military operation is commonly referred to under various names, including the Punitive Expedition, the Pancho Villa Expedition, and the Mexican Expedition. The images depict daily life, combat training, mounted patrols, camp duties, leisure time, and the general atmosphere of the camp. The notebook contains a series of notes on guard duties and various other duties, patrol messages, and several small handwritten maps of the area.
  Purchased from McBride Rare Books in 2021 (AM 2022-087).
  Military camps -- Texas -- El Paso -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Mexican-American Border Region -- photographs; Texas -- Relations -- Mexico; Notebooks -- 20th century; photographs -- 20th century; United States. Army -- History -- Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1916
- Deborah M. Garrigues Math Notebook, 1818; Garrigues, Deborah M., 1801-1876; 1 folder (Box B-001796, Folder 5)